Guide to the Committee on International Studies records, 1962-1978, bulk 1964-1977 UA.05.02.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Committee on International Studies records
1962-1978, bulk 1964-1977
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Committee on International Studies
UA.05.02.0001
5.5 Linear Feet 5 boxes
Established under a large Ford Foundation grant in 1964, the Committee on International Studies oversaw the distribution of the grant money and other sources of income to various departmental and area programs having to do with international scholarship. Spanning from 1962 to 1978, the records contain details of the committee and various subcommittee's activities during that time.
Collection Overview
The collection includes the records of the Committee on International Studies and all area program sub-committees, as well as grant and financial information from 1962 to 1978, with the bulk of the records spanning from 1964-1977. These records are comprised mostly of memoranda, correspondence, financial information, publicity materials, reports, course offerings, symposium and conference proceedings, visiting scholar information, biographical sketches, and minutes of meetings, as well as assorted documents.
Major subcommittees and centers include: African Studies, Canadian Studies, Commonwealth Studies, East Asian Studies, Hispanic Council, Latin American Studies, Middle East Studies, Russian and East European Studies, and South Asian Studies.
Further major subgroupings of note in the collection include: Cooperative Program in International Studies, Ford Foundation materials, Rockefeller Foundation materials, visiting scholar materials, faculty research materials, and US Office of Education materials.
Provenance
The Committee on Intenational Studies records were received by the Duke University Archives as a transfer in November 1977 and March 1979.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Historical note
Various sources of external support fitted together Duke University’s mosaic of programs in international studies in the two decades between 1955 and 1978. In 1955 a group of research scholars concerned with the British Commonwealth negotiated a $350,000 grant from the Carnegie-Commonwealth Fund, initiating a structured program of conferences, lectures, research, publications, and fellowships. In the 1960's United States educational institutions and the foundations that supported them were affected by a wave of interest in international studies as the nation looked outward with a mixture of interest, altruism, and fear for the first time since World War II.
The first major grant to Duke from the Ford Foundation, made in 1961, was a development grant of $400,000 which allowed the expansion and intensification of international programs. This was followed by a five-year, $900,000 grant in 1964 allocated to international programs at Duke University. This led to the establishment of the Committee on International Studies. The committee was a part of the Provost's office, coordinating and advising the provost in the establishment of budgets for individual department programs. Vice-Provost Crauford Goodwin was instrumental in helping secure the major Ford grant for the program, and became the chairman and director of the Committee on International Studies from its inception in 1964 to the spring of 1971, when he took leave from Duke University to work for the Ford Foundation to direct their program on International Studies. The chairmanship then passed temporarily to Dr. Margaret Ball as acting chair, then to Dr. Thomas F. Keller, who chaired the Committee from the fall of 1971 to the spring of 1972. Dr. Ball then took the permanent chairmanship of the committee until the spring of 1974, after which it passed to Dr. Gerald Hartwig, who was acting director until the record series ends in 1978. Marion Salinger was the administrative assistant for the committee for the duration of its recorded existence.
From the mid-1960s to the early 1970s the grant supported faculty and visiting faculty additions which brought scholars to the university with a variety of international interests and substantially strengthened the disciplines of history, economics, education, anthropology, sociology, religion, political science, and foreign languages. Due to the Ford Foundation grant Duke began offering instruction in non-western languages: Swahili, Hindi, Japanese, and Chinese, along with the necessary library staff support.
The years of 1965 through 1973 saw a massive expansion in programs in international studies, as well as new sources of funding to supplement the Ford grant. The Ford Foundation gave an additional $400,000 for a two year cooperative (Duke-UNC) post-doctoral training program for faculty from regional colleges and universities; the South Asia committee was designated an N.D.E.A. program and received financial support from the U.S. Office of Education direct support for administration, faculty, and library staff, as well as 45 fellowships. Faculty research interest was also widely supported, in part by a grant by the Rockefeller foundation and research areas ranged around the globe--from an examination of forestry schools in Europe to a study on resistance to change in Rhodesia.
With the advent of the 1970s, however, interests in area programs faded. The Ford Foundation grants ran out and were not renewed. Federal funding diminished, and the foundations withdrew support. Fellowship aid became scarce and program money was cobbled together largely through the individual efforts of faculty pursuing their own research. Interdisciplinary studies became the new vogue, while area studies faded and closed. Funding and interest shifted, but many of the programs and courses established with the seed money from the Ford Foundation and others became permanent parts of the Duke curriculum and remain active to this day. The Committee on International Studies survives today as the Office of International Affairs and Development, re-established in 1995 as an adjunct of the Provost's Office. The office is dedicated to support the University's commitment to internationalization and provide a locus for new initiatives, as well as provide development activities for this specific purpose as well as for University initiatives as a whole, and carries on the legacy of Duke’s commitment to the support of international studies to this day.
Sources Used: Notes for a Report on International Studies, Committee on International Studies records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Committee on International Studies, Committee on International Studies records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
http://www.provost.duke.edu/units/internationalaffairs.html
Russia -- Study and teaching -- United States; Committees; Latin America -- Study and teaching -- United States; Middle East -- Study and teaching -- United States; Africa -- Study and teaching -- United States; South Asia -- Study and teaching -- United States; Canada -- Study and teaching -- United States; East Asia -- Study and teaching -- United States; Hartwig, Gerald; Ball, Margaret M.; Goodwin, Craufurd D. W.; Duke University. Center for International Studies; Duke University. Committee on International Studies; Keller, Thomas; Salinger, Marion C.
- Committee on International Studies records, 1962-1978; 1
  - Council on Hispanic Research, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to Treasurer of COIS, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Introduction to the Civilizations of Southern Asia - Course Syllabi, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee on South Asian Studies - Minutes, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Commonwealth Studies Center Records, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Commonwealth Studies Center Records, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Commonwealth Studies Center Records, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Commonwealth Studies Center Records, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Commonwealth Studies Center Records, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Commonwealth Studies, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Commonwealth Studies, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Committee on Commonwealth Studies, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Committee on Commonwealth Studies - Minutes, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Joint Seminar: Economic Dimensions of the Commonwealth, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Seminar on Contemporary Canada, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Conference on Contemporary Australia, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cooperative Program in International Studies Duke-UNC Coordinating Committee, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cooperative Program in International Studies - Academic Year Program, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cooperative Program in International Studies - Summer Institute, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cooperative Program in International Studies - Budget, Correspondence with Treasurer, Annual Report, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cooperative Program in International Studies - Annual Report, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Committee on International Relations, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ford Foundation correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Supplementary Material for Ford Foundation, Program in International Training and Research, 1964 February (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ford Foundation Grant in International Studies meeting minutes, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Cooperative Program in International Studies: Correspondence, proposal, and publicity, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Sub-Saharan Africa Language and Area Center, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ford Proposal Worksheets, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Major Ford Submission, 1965 December (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Cooperative Program in International Studies Summer Institute on Southern Asia, China, and Japan, 1967 June-August (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Cooperative Program in International Studies Summer Institute on Latin America, 1968 June-August (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ford Foundation, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Ford Profile, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - History of the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program, 1965 December 3 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - International Studies at Duke University Informational Booklet, 1967 June (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Canadian Studies, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Proceedings of the Duke University Tropical Forestry Symposium; Christianity and Social Revolution in Newly Developing Nations, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Committee on Comparative Study of Social Institutions and Systems, 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Committee on the History and Comparative Study of Ideas, 1964-1970 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Committee on Professional Training, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Committee on Russian and East European Studies, 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Committee on Russian and East European Studies, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Committee on South Asian Studies, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Committee on South Asian Studies - Continuation of NDEA Language and Area Centers in Academic Year 1970-1971, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Committee on South Asian Studies, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Committee on South Asian Studies, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1972 April-October (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1971 March-June (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Report of the International Programs Subcommittee to the University Planning Committee, 1972 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Young Political Leaders (Spencer Oliver), 1974 September-November (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - 50th Anniversery Celebration, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Dr. Zhores A Medvedev, 1974 March-October (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Summer Study Seminar - Ibodan, Nigeria (Hartwig), 1975 June-December (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Dibona - Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare Teacher Training, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Hartwig Grant - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1973-1978 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare Silberman-Hartwig Proposal, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Japanese Orientation Institute, 1974 May-August (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Projected Japanese Summer Program, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Luce Professorship Program, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Lilly Endowment (Fox Proposal), 1975 January-April (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Armstrong Proposal, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Methodist Church, 1964-1975 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Donner Grant Antecedents, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Tiryakian Proposal to the Ford Foundation, 1974 January-June (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Ford Foundation - International Economic Order, 1974 February (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Possible Samizdat Research Center, 1974 June-July (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Proposed Canada/United States Center, 1974 August-November (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Tiryakian Proposal, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Treml - Department of Defense Regional Input/Output Analysis, 1975 February (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Arts and Crafts Program, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Asia Society, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Biographical Sketches for Lecture Slide Series, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Biographical Sketches for Symposium, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - East Asia Center Bulletin, 1975 October (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - China Exchange Newsletter, 1975 September (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Culcon, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Curriculum Project East Asia, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - East Asia Committee, 1975 August-October (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Committee Meeting Minutes, 1975 September (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - East Asia Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Exchange Scholars, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Education Abroad Programs, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Education Committee, 1976 February (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Enrollments and Activities, 1975 September (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Film Requisitions, 1975 October-December (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Film Evaluations, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Film Recommendation Forms, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - East Asia Center Finances, 1975 July 23 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - East Asia Grant, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - East Asia Hour, 1976 February (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Grants and Programs of Japan Foundation, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - English for Foreign Students, 1973 October (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - History 175, Undated (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Interdisciplinary Course - East Asia, 1975 August (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - East Asia Information for Final Report, 1974 September-December (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Ideas for Institutes, 1976 June-July (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Interim Report, 1975 December 30 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Japan Foundation, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Dr. Seiji Katanuma, Japanese Visiting Scholar, 1976 March-April (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Lecture Series in China, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Mailing List, Undated (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Meetings, October-December (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Minutes, 1975 October 9 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Newsletter, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Newsletters from Other Centers, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - New York Conference on Asia, 1976 February-April (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Proposal Materials, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Publicity, 1970-1976 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Research Triangle Institute Planning Group, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Seminar IDC, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Summer Institute, 1975 November (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Symposium, Quail Roost Conference Center, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Symposium Attendence, 1976 January-February (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - US-China Relations, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - TEAC, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Triangle University's Center for Advanced Studies, 1976 January 9 (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Visiting Professor Japanese Languages and Literature, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - East Asia Center, 1975 July-August (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Commerce America World Trade Outlook Issue, 1976 February 2 (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - Wingspread Report: Prospects for United States-China Relations, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - East Asia Joint Proposal, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Japan Proposal, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Rockefeller Faculty Assistance Fund, 1968-1974 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Black, David E., 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Salkin, Jay, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Whittier, Robert, 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Proctor, Harris, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Rockefeller Faculty Grants and Reimbursement, 1968-1974 (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Agency for International Development, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Effort Reports, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Ford Foundation Guideline, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Eventual Applications to Ford Foundation, 1974 June 26 (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - General Accounting Office - International Division, 1977 October-November (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - US Office of Education Publications to Further International Education, 1977 November (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - National Defense Education Act IV Awards Fellowships, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare Correspondence, 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1972-1977 (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - Proposed General Application to OE, 1978 May-June (Box 4, Folder 144)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Guidelines, 1973-1977 (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - The Asia Society Education Program, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 146)
  - National Defense Education Act VI Awards - Problem or Topic Oriented Programs (Graduate), 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 147)
  - Khartoum - Duke, 1976 October (Box 4, Folder 148)
  - Budget Recommendations, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 149)
  - Budget, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 150)
  - Terms of Ford Grant and Modification, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Subgrant Code 383-2553, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - International Studies Administration and Misc., 1974 February-October (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - Commonwealth Studies, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 154)
  - African Studies, 1973 February-March (Box 4, Folder 155)
  - South Asian Studies, 1973 February-June (Box 4, Folder 156)
  - Rockefeller Subgrant Goodwin, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 157)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 158)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1965 June-November (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - COIS Fellowships, 1971 February-May (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - COIS Fellowships, 1970 March-May (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - COIS Fellowships, 1969 March-July (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - COIS Budget, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - African Studies Committee Minutes, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Committee on African Studies, 1968-1972 (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Committee on African Studies, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - Committee on African Studies, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 168)
  - East Asian Studies, 1966-1972 (Box 5, Folder 169)
  - Doris Duke Fellowships, 1972-1977 (Box 5, Folder 170)
  - Doris Duke Professorship Fund, 1966-1977 (Box 5, Folder 171)
  - Canadian Projects, 1973 February (Box 5, Folder 172)
  - Proposed Soviet Program for Army, 1974 July-August (Box 5, Folder 173)
  - Requests for Information re: International Studies Center, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 174)
  - Director of International Studies, 1975-1977 (Box 5, Folder 175)
  - Report to International Subcommittee, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 176)
  - Center for International Studies, 1972-1975 (Box 5, Folder 177)
  - Hartwig Group, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 178)
  - Marion C Salinger, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 179)
  - International Studies Brochure, 1973 September 27 (Box 5, Folder 180)
  - Memos to COIS Committees, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 181)
  - Minutes - Meetings of COIS, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 182)
  - COIS Fellowships, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 183)
  - COIS Fellowships, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 184)
  - COIS Grant Applications, 1973 February-March (Box 5, Folder 185)
  - Annual Reports, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 186)
  - Committee on Canadian Studies, 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 187)
  - Canadian Studies Minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 188)
  - Comparative Studies, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 189)
  - Canadian Studies Awards, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 190)
  - East Asian Studies, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 191)
  - Hispanic Council, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 192)
  - Middle East Studies, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 193)
  - Russian and East European Studies, 1972-1977 (Box 5, Folder 194)
  - Social Institutions and Systems, 1974 October-November (Box 5, Folder 195)
  - South Asian Studies, 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 196)
  - Foreign Consul Generals (Visits), 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 197)
  - Visiting Senior Research Fellows, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 198)
  - Publications Ordered, 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 199)
  - Seminars, 1973 March-November (Box 5, Folder 200)
  - Visitors Center, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 201)
  - Wachovia Bank and Trust Company, 1973 February-June (Box 5, Folder 202)
  - Commonwealth Studies, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 203)
  - South Atlantic States Association for South Asian Studies, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 204)
  - African Studies Committee Shell Fellowships, 1969-1973 (Box 5, Folder 205)
  - African Studies Committee Budget, 1969-1973 (Box 5, Folder 206)
  - Committee on African Studies Misc., 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 207)
  - Committee on African Studies Speakers, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 208)
  - Inquiries, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 209)
  - African Studies Committee Minutes, 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 210)
  - Aftican Studies Committee Library Materials, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 211)
  - African Studies Committee Report Series, 1971 June (Box 5, Folder 212)
  - African Studies, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 213)
  - African Studies Committee Pan-African Track Meet, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 214)
  - African Studies Committee Appointments, 1971 April-May (Box 5, Folder 215)
  - Future of African Studies, 1971 April-June (Box 5, Folder 216)
  - African Studies Committee Correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 217)
  - Proposals for Faculty Shell Grants, 1972 October (Box 5, Folder 218)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 219)
  - Students to be Supported by COIS, 1967 February-August (Box 5, Folder 220)